Hello, and welcome to Problem Session 2 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
您好，欢迎来到 Wolfram U 的微积分课程第 2 部分。
Our topic for today is derivatives and continuity. Now being a problem session,
今天我们的主题是导数和连续性。现在是一个问题讨论环节，
we’ll discuss a few problems, but the point will be to try to show you how to solve
我们将讨论一些问题，但重点是尝试向您展示如何解决
real problems in calculus, and also how to review the concepts that you’ve learned earlier
微积分中的实际问题，以及如何通过查看实际示例来回顾您先前学到的概念。
by looking at real examples. Let’s begin with the first problem for today, and that says
让我们从今天的第一个问题开始，那就是
find the limit of x * Sin[x] + Cos[x] as x goes to π. Now keep in mind that x is continuous
找出当 x 趋近于 π 时 x * Sin[x] + Cos[x] 的极限，因为。 现在请记住，x
and so is Sin[x] and so is Cos[x], so the entire expression over here is continuous,
是连续的，Sin[x] 也是连续的，Cos[x] 也是连续的，因此这里的整个表达式是连续的
and hence what you can do is you can simply plug in the value π into it. If you do that,
因此，您可以做的就是将 π 值简单地代入其中。
then the answer is −1. You expect that the limit is going to be −1, and you can compute the limit
如果这样做，则答案是 -1。 您预计极限将为 -1，并且可以计算极限
with the Limit function and get just the same answer. Here’s a plot of the function around π,
并获得相同的答案。 这是在 π 点附近函数的图像，
and you see that the value is actually −1 around there.
您会看到该值实际为 -1。
Okay. Let’s go onto problem 2, which asks you to compute the limit of Sin[x^2 – 3x] as x approaches 3.
好的。 让我们继续研究问题 2，该问题要求您在 x 接近 3 时计算 Sin[x^2 – 3x] 的极限。
Now the point is that sine is a continuous function, so you can basically take the limit
现在关键是正弦是一个连续函数，因此您基本上可以在此处
inside the bracket over here and work out that simple limit, which is just 9 – 9, so that’s 0.
获得括号内的极限，并计算出这个简单的极限，即 9 – 9，因此为0。
You expect the limit is going to be 0 for the entire expression, and you can confirm that with Limit
您预计整个表达式的极限将为 0，并且可以使用
and get back the same answer, 0. Here is a plot, and the plot shows you
Limit 函数确认并得到相同的答案 0。这是一个图，该图向您显示
that indeed the limit is 0 at x = 3.
确实在 x = 3 时极限为 0。
Okay. Problem 3 asks you to find the limit as x approaches 9 of this function over here.
好的。 问题 3 要求在 x 趋近 9 时此函数的极限。
Now the point is that when x is 9, we have an issue because the denominator becomes 0 at x = 9
现在的要点是，当 x 为 9 时，我们遇到一个问题，因为在 x = 9
because that’s 81 − 81. That’s 0, so you can not evaluate the limit that the quotient law as given to you.
时分母变为0，因为那是 81-81。也就是 0，所以您不能直接通过商定律求极限。
But what you can do is to try and cancel a common factor by first multiplying the top and the bottom
但是，您可以做的是先试着在分子分母同乘
by 3 + √x, and if we do that, you see that we now have the required factor 9 – x,
3 + √x ，以尝试消除公因子，然后，如果执行此操作，您会看到我们现在有所需的公因数 9 – x，
which cancels with the denominator, and if you do that, you can simplify. Then you get back
该因数与分母相抵消，如果这样做，您可以化简表达式。 你会得到一个
an expression which no longer has any problem with computing limits. If you now plug in x = 9,
不再对计算极限有任何问题的表达式。如果现在代入 x = 9
you would expect to get 54 over here, so the answer is 1/54 for this limit.
那么您会期望得到 54，所以该极限的答案是 1/54。
That’s a bit difficult because you had to do some work to get to the answer,
这有点困难，因为您必须做一些工作才能计算答案，
but typically limits of rational functions or rational expressions are a bit more complicated.
但是通常有理函数或有理表达式的极限要复杂一些。
Problem 4 asks you to show that there is a root of this expression over here between 2 and 3.
问题 4 要求您证明此表达式的根在 2 到 3 之间。
Now that should remind you of the intermediate value theorem, which says that
现在应该使您想起中间值定理，该中间值定理表示
the if sign of the expression is different at the two ends, then you actually have a root in the middle.
表达式的符号在区间两端点处不同，那么实际上根一定在区间内。
If you compute the expression at 2 you get −5 point something, and at 3 you get a positive number.
如果在 2 处计算表达式，则得到 −5 点，在 3 处得到正数。
You have a negative value at one end, a positive value at the other end, so there must be
您在一端有一个负值，在另一端有一个正值，因此在2到3的区间内
a root in the interval 2 to 3. You can confirm that with Solve, and actually you compute the value,
必有一个根。您可以使用 Solve 函数确认这一点，并实际上计算出该值，
which is about 2.39. Here’s the plot, and you can see the function does becomes 0 around 2.4,
大约是 2.39。这是图像，您可以看到该函数在 2.4 周围确实变为 0，因此与 Solve 给出的值一致。
so that agrees with the value given by Solve. Like we said earlier on, the intermediate value theorem
就像我们之前说的，中间值定理
is a very powerful tool for identifying roots of functions.
是函数求根的非常强大的工具。
Okay. Problem 5 says find the value of a which will make this piecewise expression continuous,
好的。 问题 5 表示计算某个 a 的值，使该分段表达式连续，
and clearly the only problem is at 1. Now what you need to do is to fit the value of a
显然唯一的问题是在 1。现在您需要做的就是拟合 a 的值
so the function becomes continuous at 1. Now at 1, if you work out the function value it’s 3,
因此该函数在 1 点变为连续。现在在 1 点，如果计算出该函数的值为 3，
and the limit from the right-hand side is also 3 because if you plug in 1 over here,
并且右极限也是 3，因为如果您在此处代入1，
you get back 3, so you need to fit the value of a so that the left-hand limit is 3 as well.
得到 3，因此您需要拟合 a的值，以使左极限也为 3。
You can do that with the Solve function, and get a to be 6. Now once you do that,
您可以使用 Solve 函数来做到这一点，并将 a 设为 6。现在，一旦完成
then the function becomes 6x − 3 instead of 8x − 3 for x less than 1, and if you plot it now,
在 x 小于一时函数为 6x − 3 而不是 8x − 3，如果现在画出它，
it looks nice and continuous—although it does have a corner over here—but there is
它看起来不错且连续, 尽管这里确实有一个角, 但那里的
no problem with the continuity. a = 6 is required for making this expression continuous at 1.
连续性没有问题。 要使该表达式在1处连续，需要 a = 6。
Problem 6 says find the limit of (1/x – 1/3)/(x – 3). Now that’s just a derivative
问题 6 要计算 (1/x – 1/3)/(x – 3) 的极限。
because that’s like a difference quotient. You can work out the answer using D,
现在这只是一个导数，因为这就像一个差商。 您可以使用 D 算出答案，
or you could work out the limit directly and get back the same answer.
或者您可以直接计算出极限并得到相同的答案。
Here is a plot which shows that in fact you do have a tangent line at this point over here.
这是图像，它表明实际上您在这一点确实有一条切线。
Working the limit in this case could be done either by using D or by doing a limit calculation.
在这种情况下，可以通过使用 D 函数或直接计算来得到极限。
Okay. Problem number 7 says compute the left-hand derivative of this expression at 1.
好的。 问题 7 要求计算此表达式在 1 点的左导数。
First we set up the function f[x] with the given expression. You want to find the left-hand derivative,
首先，我们使用给定的表达式定义函数 f[x]。 您想计算左导数，
so you can use DifferenceQuotient with the Direction option. You say FromBelow.
因此您可以将 DifferenceQuotient 与 Direction 选项一起使用。 设置 Direction 为 FromBelow。
You want to go from the left at x = 1, and you get back the answer. Then what you can do is
左侧趋近 x = 1，然后得到答案。
you can use that answer, which is just like the slope, to work out the tangent line,
然后，您可以做的就是用这个答案, 相当于切线方程的斜率,来计算切线，
and you see that indeed you have a tangent line at the required point.
并且您看到确实在所需点处有一条切线。
But notice that you have a problem at 1. This is just going to be the left-hand derivative.
但是请注意，您在 1 处有一个问题。这只是左导数。
Okay. Let’s go on now to find the derivative of this expression at 2. Now because you have
好的。现在继续在 2 点处计算该表达式的导数。现在，由于您具有
an absolute value, what you could do is analyze the expression a bit more
绝对值，因此您可以做的是对表达式进行更多分析
and say that because 2 is less than 3, so the expression becomes 4 * (−x + 3),
因为 2 小于 3 ，所以表达式变为 4 * (−x + 3),
and then work out the derivative of that, which is just −4. Or you can simply use D itself
然后求出该表达式的导数，即 −4。 或者您可以简单地对原表达式
on the original function and get back just the same answer. What you can do finally is
使用 D 函数, 并获得相同的答案。
to plot the derivative and original expression, the tangent line, and what you see over here is that
最后您可以绘制导数和原始表达式，切线，然后在这可以看到
in fact you have a coincidence of tangent line with the function on the left, and that’s very typical of
实际上，切线与函数左侧重合，这是绝对值函数的
of the absolute value function—namely, the tangent line will overlap the graph at some stage.
典型特征，即切线在某一区间会与函数图像重叠。
Okay. Problem number 9 says compute the values of a and b for which this function
好的。 问题 9 表示计算使该函数可导的 a 和 b
becomes differentiable. Now that’s a much a harder problem because you need to check that
的值。 这是一个更困难的问题，因为您需要检查一下
that you actually have the same left-hand and right-hand derivatives, and you also need to
确实有相同的左导数和右导数，并且您还需要满足
some kind of continuity. Okay. We’re talking about derivatives. If you work out
连续性。 好的。 我们讨论一下导数。 如果算出
the derivative on the left. That’s 3x^2 + a, so at 2, the answer is going to be 12 + a.
左导数。是 3x^2 + a，所以在 2 点，左导数是 12 + a。
That must be equal to the derivative that’s over here, which is 2bx – 3, so that must be 4b.
该值必须等于此处的导数 2bx – 3，因此必须为 4b。
If you work out the left-hand limits, then you see over here when you plug in 2, you get 8 + 2a,
如果算出左极限，那么代入 2 后，您会得到 8 + 2 a，
and over there you get 4b – 3. Now both those must be satisfied for getting the values of a and b,
然后在这一点得到 4b – 3。现在必须满足这两个条件才能获取  a 和 b
so you solve the system and you get back a  as 1 and b as 13/4. Once you’ve got those values,
的值，因此您可以解方程组，您得到 a 为 1，b 为 13/4。 获得这些值后，
you can then plot everything and check that in fact you have a nice smooth expression over here.
然后，您可以把这些都画出来, 并检查您是否在此处有平滑的函数表达式。
Okay. Let’s go on now to number 10, which says compute the tangent line of this function at 1.
好的。 现在继续到第 10 题，计算此函数在 1 处的切线。
Now to compute the tangent line, you first of all need to find a value of the function at 1.
现在，要计算切线，首先需要计算在 1 点的函数值。
You need to compute the slope at x = 1. You’ve got both those now. Then the tangent line
您需要计算在 x = 1 时的斜率。 然后切线
is y – y1 equal to slope times (x – x1). That’s the equation of the tangent line,
方程是 y – y1 等于斜率乘 (x – x1)。这就是切线的方程式，
and then you can do that over here to get a plot. You’ve got a plot now which shows clearly
然后您可以在此处进行此操作以获得图像。现在您已经有了一张图，可以清楚地显示
that we’ve got the right tangent line in this case.
在这种情况下，我们有正确的切线。
Okay. Problem 11 says compute the normal line to a function at 4. Now the normal line,
好的。问题 11 要计算到一个函数在 4 点的法线。现在，请记住，法线垂直于切线。
keep in mind, is perpendicular to the tangent line. Of course you first find the value at 4.
当然，您首先会计算 4 的值。
Then you compute the derivative at 4. The answer is −10. Now −10 is the slope of the tangent line,
然后，您在 4 处计算导数。答案是 -10。
so the slope of the normal must be 1/10. Use that information to work out
现在 -10 是切线的斜率，因此法线的斜率一定是 1/10。使用该条件求
the equation of the normal over here, and then finally we plot the original function
此处的法线方程，最后我们绘制原始函数
along with the normal line at 4. You do see that the normal line is perpendicular to
以及过 4 点的法线。您确实看到法线垂直于
the curve at that point, and of course it’s perpendicular to the tangent line at that point.
该点处的曲线，当然这说的是它垂直于该点的切线。
Problem number 12 says that you’re given the position vector of a particle s[t]
问题12 求粒子 s[t] 的位置矢量
and you want to find the acceleration of that particle at a certain time, namely, t = 3π/2.
并且您想要计算某个时间的那个粒子的加速度，即 t = 3π/2。
Now the acceleration is the second derivative of the position, so you compute the second derivative.
现在，加速度是位置的二阶导数，因此您可以计算二阶导数。
That’s the shorthand for the second derivative of the position. Then you plug in the t as 3π/2,
这是该点的二阶导数的简写。 然后将 t 代入为 3π/2 ，
and you get back the value. Then you can use that to actually plot both
得到二阶导数值。 然后您可以使用它来绘制
the position and the acceleration, and that’s the plot of both those functions.
位置和加速度，这就是这两个函数的图。
The accretion is the second time derivative of the position.
加速度是位置对时间的二阶导数。
Problem number 13 says that you’re given a table of values, and from a table of values
问题 13 表示给定一个值表，并希望从函数
for a function f[x], you want to compute the average rate of change of that function
f[x] 的值表中计算出该函数
over the range 6 to 12. Now the average rate simply means the slope of the secant line
在 6 到 12 之间的平均变化率。现在，平均变化率就是这两点之间的割线的斜率，
between those two points, so you work it out. The values are 14 and 10 at those two points.
因此您可以进行计算。这两个点的函数值分别为 14 和 10。
We will divide (14 – 10) by (12 – 6), and you get back the average rate of change.
我们将 (14 – 10) 除以 (12 – 6)，然后得出平均变化率。
Here’s a plot of the points in secant line. Of course secant line is not a very good approximation,
这是割线上的散点图。
but often all that you have is a table of values.
当然，割线并不是一个很好的近似值，但是通常您所拥有的只是一张值表。
And finally, problem 14, which says compute the instantaneous rate of change of z
最后，问题 14 要求计算 z
with respect to y for this function over here when y is π. Now when we say
相对于 y 在y 等于 π 点的瞬时变化率
instantaneous rate of change, what we mean is the derivative. You simply work out D at that point.
现在，当我们说瞬时变化率时，我们指的是导数。您只需在那点计算出 D 即可。
That’s the instantaneous rate of change, and then using that, you can work out the tangent line.
这就是瞬时变化率，然后使用它可以计算出切线。
When you do that, you actually see that you have the tangent line over here given by
当您进行此操作时，您实际上看到的是此处的切线，
the instantaneous rate of change as its slope.
该切线由瞬时变化率作为其斜率给出。
To summarize, the key concept for this problem was that the instantaneous rate of change
总而言之，此问题的关键概念是
is the slope of the tangent line at that point. This brings me to the end of today’s problem session.
瞬时变化率是该点处切线的斜率。今天的问题环节结束了。
I hope that you have benefited from the discussion. Do review the problems, and then in Lesson 9,
我希望您从以上讨论中受益。
we’ll go on to talking about differentiation rules. But before doing that,
请复习一下习题，然后在第 9 课中，我们将继续讨论微分规则。但是在那之前
there is a small quiz for you to take. Do take Quiz 2, and then you’ll be ready for Lesson 9.
有一个小测验供您完成。 完成测验 2，然后就可以开始第 9 课了。
Thank you very much. I hope that you’ve enjoyed today’s lesson. I’ll stop over here.
非常感谢你。 希望您喜欢今天的课程。 我会在这里停下来。
(翻译: 秦晋 北京师范大学)